<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>M. Harrington's Parallel unparallel'd: or, A demonstration upon it, and the parable opened. Wherein it appears, neither the spirit of the people, nor the spirit of men like Mr. R. but the spirit of God, of Christ, of his people in the Parliament, and adherents to the cause, is the fittest for the government of the Commonwealth, Zach. 4. 6.</title>
            <author>Rogers, John, 1627-1665?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91935</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866856</idno>
  <idno type="VID">119144</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240948826</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1810</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E999_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207828</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866856</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99866856e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91935)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119144)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 148:E999[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>M. Harrington's Parallel unparallel'd: or, A demonstration upon it, and the parable opened. Wherein it appears, neither the spirit of the people, nor the spirit of men like Mr. R. but the spirit of God, of Christ, of his people in the Parliament, and adherents to the cause, is the fittest for the government of the Commonwealth, Zach. 4. 6.</title>
                  <author>Rogers, John, 1627-1665?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept: 22. 1659.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Harrington, James, 1611-1677. --  Parallel of the spirit of the people.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119144:1"/>
            <head>M. <hi>Harrington</hi>'s Parallel Unparallel'd: OR, A <hi>Demonstration</hi> upon it, and the <hi>Parable</hi> opened.</head>
            <head type="sub">Wherein it appears, <hi>Neither the</hi> Spirit of the People, <hi>nor the</hi> Spirit of men <hi>like Mr.</hi> R. <hi>but the</hi> Spirit of God, <hi>of Christ, of his</hi> People <hi>in</hi> Parliament, <hi>and</hi> Adherents <hi>to the Cause, is the fittest for the Government of the Commonwealth,</hi> Zach. 4.6.</head>
            <p>THe Repute which I have retained of Mr. <hi>Harrington's</hi> Person and Parts, has put an <hi>Act of Prohibition</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my hands (as I take my <hi>Pen</hi>) to avoid personal <hi>Reflection;</hi> as well as an <hi>oblivion</hi> of <hi>his,</hi> and of any <hi>others</hi> incomposure of mind or <hi>Oratory</hi> that I have met with; not worthy the ingenuity either of <hi>Man</hi> or <hi>Christian:</hi> In the Principles of <hi>both</hi> being so propense to serve him and them (in the Love of the <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>Cause</hi> contended for,) that having Read the <hi>Bill</hi> thrice over already, and <hi>yast</hi> it, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess I am more ready to wipe <hi>my Pen</hi> upon my <hi>own Skirt,</hi> then on <hi>his</hi> or theirs. Yet common sence (I presume) will allow me the <hi>common liberty</hi> of animadverting or making a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon judgement with other men upon the <hi>Paper-Kite</hi> that flew about the last week (without his <hi>Anger</hi> be it, for we are both <hi>in jest!</hi>) and whatever he conceives of me, (with the Lords grace!) I will rather sing to his <hi>Passions</hi> as <hi>Nurses</hi> do to Babes, <hi>Hush! — Lullaby!</hi> then let out my own.</p>
            <p>But I must confess, to fly a <hi>Kite,</hi> I did ever take for <hi>Boys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play</hi> until now; being surpriz'd with the <hi>Novelty</hi> and <hi>Noise</hi> of it, I began to gaze for company, and found his Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be the benefit of the <hi>Wind,</hi> or of <hi>Popular applause,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> (and in many things deservedly) hath to help him. With which confidence he is pleased to <hi>shoot</hi> it up into the open Air, <hi>hisce verbis</hi> at the Neck of it, <hi>viz. Whether the spirit of the People, or of men like Mr.</hi> R. <hi>be fitter to be trusted with the Government.</hi> By <hi>J. Harrington:</hi> and there he holds
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119144:2"/>it, as an <hi>Appeal</hi> to the Observer. A pretty! (imprudenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al) <hi>sport!</hi> yet I cannot choose but smile! and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>I have committed it to memory, that so much humanity is (yet) left me, as not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy others the matter and occasion</hi> (he gives) <hi>to laugh with me.</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>O imitatores! — ut mihi saepè</l>
                  <l>Bilem, saepè jocum Vestri movere tumultus.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>As the make of it is <hi>inartificial,</hi> the matter <hi>irrational</hi> and ungrounded, so the <hi>Motion</hi> of it (or the flight) as <hi>hobling</hi> and <hi>headlong</hi> as the rest, without <hi>equality,</hi> balance, or impartiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>Headed</hi> with an Appeal; but <hi>Winged</hi> with a <hi>Parallel</hi> of Spirits, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>spirit of the People!</hi> and the <hi>spirit of</hi> Mr. <hi>R.</hi> tatter'd, hackled, and shagg'd on purpose to make it <hi>mount</hi> and fly apace! but with a short <hi>bob-tail;</hi> and yet two lines of <hi>Apology</hi> is tyed to it, to make it fly the better, and to informe us, that it was <hi>the imployment of two or three hours in a rainy day;</hi> which we need not question from the <hi>Dirtiness</hi> indeed of the whole stuff. But (with <hi>Civility</hi> to so worthy a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son) seeing I am at leasure for an hour or two also, to answer his mirth, if not his mind; I must consider his <hi>Parallel, p.</hi> 1, 2. (to pass by the undue <hi>Character</hi> which he gives of me, and of men of my judgement (but what he means by it, I know not, neither doth he determine it, unless in this) that they take the <hi>People for prophane wretches, &amp;c.</hi> Whereas indeed we take the people for the <hi>faithful ones,</hi> adherents to the Cause and Commonwealth, or for the Body in Sanity; and not for <hi>profane wretches;</hi> Nor yet <hi>prophane wretches,</hi> haters of the godly, <hi>and persecutors, &amp;c,</hi> for the people, as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> does.)</p>
            <p>To his 1. <hi>Par. That the Spirit of a people where they live by a King, will obey a King very faithfully; But Mr.</hi> R. <hi>is not for a King upon any Terms whatsoever.</hi> Behold the <hi>Parallel!</hi> by which he grants that this of mine is as <hi>Right and strait a line</hi> of Reason as his <hi>own,</hi> (or as that he calls the Peoples,) else it cannot be <hi>Parallel;</hi> and also it must be produced in one and the same <hi>Superficies,</hi> which contains the <hi>longitude</hi> and <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude</hi> of the Commonwealth: and why then doth he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119144:2"/>of it? if we give as much to the <hi>whole people</hi> as is their <hi>Right,</hi> or as they can desire for their <hi>Weal?</hi> But if on our <hi>Parts</hi> and on <hi>his</hi> (or the <hi>Peoples</hi>) he will needs have us stand like <hi>Parallel-lines</hi> at an <hi>Aequi-distance</hi> to run <hi>ad insinitum,</hi> and never meet; (only for discriminating <hi>good and bad,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents and Delinquents, <hi>sound and unsound,</hi> according to the <hi>Nature,</hi> Reason, and <hi>Righteousness</hi> of our <hi>Cause,</hi> and indeed the best formes of all <hi>Commonwealths,</hi>) <hi>I have not so learned Christ,</hi> nor the Publick; neither have I learned so little <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> but that a <hi>twofold use</hi> I know may be made, even of <hi>Parallel-lines</hi> for the <hi>Publick service,</hi> either of which I offer as an <hi>expedient</hi> to <hi>Ʋnite</hi> us, if it may be by any <hi>Art,</hi> Reason (or <hi>grace</hi>) effected. As 1. To make a <hi>Quadrate</hi> or <hi>perfect square,</hi> wherein on all sides of the Commonwealth, the People (that have not forfeited) may find their <hi>Rights,</hi> immunities and <hi>Liberties</hi> (Civil and Spiritual) all alike, in <hi>equal,</hi> even, and full <hi>proportions;</hi> so as no one <hi>party,</hi> sort, side, nor faction, may have more <hi>Interest</hi> or <hi>Dominion</hi> then another, in this <hi>sound body</hi> of Adherents, but to be <hi>square</hi> on all sides. This is the <hi>Platforme</hi> of the <hi>New Jerusalem,</hi> Rev. 21.16. <hi>The City lieth four square, and the length is large as the breadth: the length, the breadth, and the height of it are equal.</hi> So <hi>Ezek</hi> 48. And in this forme was the <hi>Camp of Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, Numb.</hi> 1. that Military <hi>Republick,</hi> and must be ours before we come to a full point. 2. To <hi>draw</hi> a <hi>Right-line</hi> through this <hi>Parallel,</hi> or these two, <hi>viz,</hi> the <hi>spirit of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, with the spirit of the other;</hi> This shall make both sides equal, and useful, as I could enucleate it with admirable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstration and reason. Now the <hi>Right-line</hi> is the <hi>interest of Christ</hi> in the Nations, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. <hi>Isa.</hi> 28.17. and the <hi>Cause</hi> contended for, (which is a <hi>Plumb-line,</hi> Amos 7.7. and a <hi>Measuring-line,</hi> Zach. 2.1.) This running through us, will <hi>knit</hi> and unite us, as the <hi>ewes and Gentiles</hi> at a greater di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, Ephes. 2.14. <hi>For he is our peace,</hi> Micah. 5.4, 5. <hi>and <hi>this,</hi> this man shall be <hi>the Peace.</hi>
               </hi> Neither is it a <hi>Parable</hi> (if a <hi>Parallel</hi>) to Mr. <hi>H.</hi> his own Reason, that we should be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst any other <hi>King</hi> in the Commonwealth, seeing the People can subsist, and that <hi>best</hi> too without it.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119144:3"/>
            <p> His 2. Par. <hi>The people where they subsist by Lords, are faithful to their Lords,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But the spirit of Mr.</hi> R. <hi>is not for the Government of Lords, or such as might pretend to any Reason of their Government: but for the Government of a few that cannot pretend such Reason,</hi> &amp;c. Not of Lords, because we can live without them; and better too, or with more free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. But to say, we are not for such as have the best <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of Government,</hi> and <hi>Right</hi> too in the whole World, is a <hi>false witness</hi> nor have I argued for the Government of a few, that have no <hi>Reason to Rule,</hi> in arguing for the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and People (Adhering to the <hi>Cause</hi>) who have both the <hi>Reason</hi> and <hi>Right</hi> too.</p>
            <p>To his 3. Par. <hi>The spirit of Mr.</hi> R. <hi>is not only to have a people that can live of themselves, to be governed by none other but such as himself; but throwing away all modesty, is a profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed enemy to any man, that at such a streight shall fairly offer a charity to the people, or service to his Country.</hi> This <hi>Bill</hi> is as long as a <hi>Taylors,</hi> who takes measure of other men, but not of himself; nor is there the least colour of <hi>Reason</hi> or <hi>Truth</hi> in the charge (or charity in it) seeing Mr. <hi>R.</hi> (a poor despised dust!) is so conscious of his own imbecility and unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, that he professes it before God and men, the <hi>highest ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> he aims at, in this world, is to be but <hi>humble</hi> and holy! <hi>faithful</hi> and serviceable! among the meanest of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren! in the <hi>interest of Christ,</hi> and the <hi>Commonwealth!</hi> And had rather (incomparably) be one in <hi>subjection</hi> then in <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority!</hi> at the Lords <hi>foot,</hi> then mans <hi>head!</hi> in the number of the <hi>holiest,</hi> then of the <hi>highest!</hi> and to have a <hi>Government</hi> over his <hi>own Spirit,</hi> then over any man on earth! Prov. 25.28. and 16.32. <hi>For he that ruleth his spirit, is better then he that taketh a City.</hi> And the Lord is his witness, how little it ever was so much as in his thought, what Mr. <hi>H.</hi> hath exhibited as a charge! his utmost ambition is to be <hi>governed</hi> in an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for the good of all; and to contend in virtue with the good, not with the great! Neither hath any Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course dropped from his Pen or Lips, for any one <hi>Party,</hi> Sect or <hi>Faction,</hi> but for the <hi>whole body</hi> of the <hi>well-affected,</hi> (for the which he hath published three Treatises with strenuous <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119144:3"/>too to propagate it.) Nor is he an enemy, (much less a professed one) <hi>to any man that shall offer a charity to the People, or service to his Country;</hi> but if to any, to him that does it not; or does all he can against them <hi>without charity</hi> when emerging; so to impose a <hi>Platform</hi> inconsistent with the being and well-being of our <hi>Cause,</hi> is but little Charity to the one, or service to the other. Charity must have eyes as well as hands; and though she give her branches, yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain her Roots. It was as much <hi>Charity</hi> in <hi>Edward</hi> 6th. to give a <hi>Bridewel</hi> for the <hi>Sinner,</hi> as an <hi>Hospital</hi> for the <hi>Sick:</hi> and what do we say more? <hi>only discriminate!</hi> And yet to the one and the other in the Commonwealth is <hi>Mine</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, so as rather then hinder the service of another, I do profer my own most cordially with the Sacrifice of my life (for the good of my <hi>Country!</hi> and glory of my Christ!) <hi>Tam dulce &amp; decorum est pro Patriâ mori.</hi> And therefore God forgive him this incogitancy! and censure so groundless! that whiles he looks for more <hi>Modesty</hi> in me, he does not loose it in himself! or respect the gift, and reject the grace! or occasion the Turkish lamentation, Our <hi>Mustapha is dead! O Mustapha! <hi>Mustapha!</hi>
               </hi> the <hi>flower of Chivalry!</hi> to be said of <hi>Charity</hi> by such a Liberty <hi>audacter calumniari.</hi> Seeing as <hi>Aristides</hi> once said, <hi>It is the part of a good Citizen to do good against evil,</hi> and of a good Commonwealths-men to <hi>rejoyce in good things, and not in good words,</hi> or high <hi>Encomiums,</hi> no more then to be discouraged by <hi>bad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither deals he so ingenuously or candidly as he ought, in Quoting the words of p. 70. <hi>In the words of</hi> Hen. 8. <hi>from their old Mumpsimus and his new Sumpsimus,</hi> &amp;c. for he wholly omits the Author, <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and makes them mine, saying, <hi>He should be fined</hi> 5 <hi>li.</hi> but this is no <hi>Common-prayer</hi> (Sir,) but a special one! nor is it a <hi>fine</hi> for quoting an <hi>Author,</hi> but in the <hi>Roman Commonwealth</hi> for fixing a slander, was there a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere one; and when the Crimes could not be proved, the false <hi>Accusers</hi> had their legs broken: but I had rather he should <hi>break my head,</hi> then have that <hi>Law</hi> of force, unless to <hi>break the legs</hi> of his mistaken Conclusions and <hi>false Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters</hi> of us; and to indear him the more by it to the truth,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119144:4"/>righteousness and holiness of a Commonwealth, or Christian Constitution; which is all the Contest between us, (<hi>viz.</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Nature of the Commonwealth) and though in other things he be far my Superior, yet in this I humbly think him short. And therefore as in construing <hi>Latine</hi> we give the Adjective to the more worthy Gender, where the Substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives be many, if we keep the <hi>concord;</hi> so where the <hi>Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes</hi> of Commonwealths are many, let us keep to that which is most worthy in it's Gender, Nature, Case, and number, <hi>i. e.</hi> a holy, Christian, and <hi>Theocratick Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth;</hi> and not a <hi>Heathenish</hi> nor a <hi>Popish</hi> Platforme.</p>
            <p>But the main body of this <hi>Gentlemans Paper</hi> mounts better then the <hi>Parallel;</hi> and possibly with much more applause, <hi>p.</hi> 2, 3. by a <hi>prety Artifice,</hi> to evade our Argument; for, he finds fault with two <hi>Greek quot.</hi> Englished; In the first he hath got the <hi>start</hi> indeed, at which I was a little amazed: I inquired the matter, and found it to be a meer <hi>Errata</hi> of the <hi>Printer,</hi> that helped him at a dead lift, (of which are too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in that <hi>Treatise</hi>) for I went to the <hi>Printer,</hi> who had all the Copy in his Custody, and upon the search together, we both saw the word <hi>(to)</hi> left out, in <hi>p.</hi> 72. That in <hi>Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon none stood up</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>assurgunt,</hi> or rose <hi>ex aliquo loco,</hi> out of any place) <hi>praeterquam Regi &amp; ephoro,</hi> but to a King and the Ephor (or one of the Court of the <hi>Ephors,</hi>) the word <hi>to</hi> being <hi>slipt</hi> out at <hi>Press,</hi> alters the <hi>Case,</hi> but not the <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> which is, that a <hi>Single Person</hi> hath an easie access by such a <hi>Platforme</hi> of a Commonwealth. Nor could he in Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son have suggested it mine (who have been a Student in that <hi>Tongue</hi> above this 20. years) unless my late sufferings had so impoverished me, as to make me wholly ignorant of the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>Case.</hi>
               </hi> But (suppose the <hi>Case</hi> lost in two letters) doth this enervate the <hi>Example?</hi> or Sequel of a <hi>Single Persons</hi> rise from the practise and principles of <hi>Heathen Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths?</hi> The other <hi>Quotat.</hi> out of <hi>Heraclid.</hi> is as I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly <hi>Englished,</hi> and not as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> hath <hi>sensed</hi> or sentenced it; The <hi>Thesmothets</hi> were sworn, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>not to take gifts</hi> (for bribes,) <hi>nor to put up the golden Statue:</hi> Mr. <hi>H.</hi> would have it, <hi>or if they did, they were
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119144:4"/>to pay a Statue of Gold.</hi> But to make it <hi>sense,</hi> it is his own; for the <hi>Conjunction,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is not <hi>disjunctive</hi> but <hi>Copulative,</hi> so that in the <hi>Grammer</hi> of it, <hi>(&amp; respectu Potestatis)</hi> under submission, I say, It must be Construed as I have rendred it, unless there had been some private Reason in the <hi>latter,</hi> repugnant and gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saying to the <hi>former,</hi> to alter the <hi>Concord;</hi> which is the only exception that I know of in the <hi>Rule.</hi> Wherefore to swear them <hi>not to do this, or that,</hi> is as elegantly exprest, and as tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Construed, <hi>neither</hi> (or not) <hi>to do this nor that,</hi> seeing the <hi>Negative</hi> rules both. A many instances in <hi>oratory</hi> I have by me; but that upon <hi>search</hi> I have found one (more famous then either of us) who translates this <hi>very Greek</hi> long since after the same Rule with me; his words are, <hi>Solemne juramentum praestare solebant justè se in Magistratu versaturos, dona non accepturos, <hi>nec</hi> Auream Statuam posituros.</hi> Whose <hi>Learning,</hi> Reason, Interest and Understanding so far surpassing mine (if not his) in Antient <hi>Language,</hi> Authors, and <hi>Commonwealths,</hi> is unquestionable all over <hi>Europe;</hi> and of sufficient validity and credit to rescue my <hi>Quotation</hi> or <hi>Translation</hi> from Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s Invasion. But by this (saith he) Mr. <hi>R. understands a King;</hi> and what needs that? seeing the next words are (which Mr. <hi>H.</hi> omits) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. But the <hi>
                  <hi>King</hi> (who was one of the <hi>Archons</hi>) did di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spense the power which appertain'd to sacrifices and to Wars.</hi> Who must needs be more then <hi>King-priest,</hi> or <hi>King-herald,</hi> that hath the <hi>Administration</hi> of Wars and Peace. The Rectify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Readers judgement in these, was the grand <hi>induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of putting pen to paper, and not to vindicate my self so much; seeing he that seeketh his <hi>own revenge,</hi> serveth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self more then the truth, and besides that, intrencheth upon God's <hi>Prerogative</hi> of <hi>Judge and Avenger.</hi> And as I have my ends, if I can but divert the <hi>force</hi> and <hi>fury</hi> of others from them <hi>in power</hi> (though upon my self) for the <hi>Publick's</hi> sake; So am I as much honoured in my <hi>Antagonist;</hi> so Noble and so <hi>worthy a person</hi> (as I judge Mr. <hi>H.</hi> to be) doth make the Honour of the reflection, a Corrective to the Humor; and the Credit of it, to the smart. It was a pitiful complaint of poor <hi>Aristides</hi> (the <hi>Locrian</hi>) when he was bit with a <hi>Weasel</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119144:5"/>very dangerously, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that it had been much more pleasing to him, if it been by a <hi>Lyon</hi> or a <hi>Leopard,</hi> or such a (noble) creature; but to receive it from so contemptible a beast, did afflict him more with the ignominy then with his death.</p>
            <p>There remains but little more of Reply; only the <hi>Sides</hi> of the <hi>Paper</hi> (to help it's flight) are stitch'd or starched up in some haste, (in four or five places;) as first, <hi>p.</hi> 2. where he frets (a little too much) at an innocent wish that he were <hi>as much against Anarchy and Atheism;</hi> which (without the <hi>Art,</hi> or least intent of Slandring) he might the better have waved as to himself, had it not been too visible a <hi>Character</hi> of others (mainly intended) in the same <hi>Club,</hi> when <hi>that</hi> was attended for <hi>Trump about.</hi> But although Mr. <hi>H.</hi> be a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Gentleman, yet I would not think him so impatient or imprudent, for the loss of a peny to cast away the purse; or of one ear, to fire the sheaf. A nobleman in the <hi>Court</hi> of the Emperor <hi>Rodolph.</hi> 2. bringing a <hi>Chrystal-glass</hi> full of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the morning to wash the <hi>Emperours face,</hi> let fall the <hi>Cover</hi> unawares, at which he dash'd apieces the whole Glass for anger; but if the <hi>Cover</hi> be lost, it doth not hurt the <hi>Glass</hi> or his credit in those principles that are clear, pure and Chrystal for a Commonwealth. So in <hi>p.</hi> 3. upon <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> he repeats my words, and then cries, <hi>Well-bowl'd</hi> Mr. <hi>R.</hi> I believe so too, for I have hit the JACK I am sure; and I am much mistaken if my <hi>Ground</hi> be not the best of any yet set, <hi>viz. for a Christian or Theocratick Commonwealth;</hi> yea, this I may add, that my <hi>Bias</hi> is in my <hi>Bowl,</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> a <hi>principle,</hi>) whiles most mens <hi>Bowls</hi> are in the <hi>Bias,</hi> (viz. <hi>of the Times,</hi> let them turn as they will.) So in the same <hi>page,</hi> saith he, <hi>Steal a little more, and say his Cake is dough!</hi> which if I do, it shall be from the Prophet, Hos. 7.8. <hi>Ephraim hath <hi>mixed</hi> himself among the people! Ephraim is a <hi>Cake</hi> not <hi>turned!</hi>
               </hi> or <hi>dough</hi> on one side! <hi>viz.</hi> on that side wherein he mixes with the multitude! or the spirit of the <hi>Heathen Nations!)</hi> In which sense only, we are against <hi>
                  <hi>his</hi> Rotation</hi> (and not in it's self a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it;) and so we say, it was not in the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119144:5"/>
               <hi>Israel,</hi> nor can it be in a <hi>Christian,</hi> therefore much <hi>ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> is not requisite to answer that. As for another way (dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepant to Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s) of <hi>Liberty of Conscience</hi> in the <hi>worship and service of God</hi> I it hath been all along stated and exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to us (in some measure) more <hi>responsable</hi> to our <hi>Cause,</hi> and <hi>Reasonable</hi> in our <hi>Consciences,</hi> then the <hi>National Rule,</hi> or <hi>Conscience</hi> which he proposes; (adequate to his new De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitiou of man, by nature (Aphor. 27.) <hi>rather a Religious then a rational Creature,</hi> So that, <hi>the leading which the major part of man kind gives up to, in matters of Religion,</hi> must be the <hi>National</hi> Rule, <hi>Aphor.</hi> 31, 32. in his opinion.) But thus (I hope) without much heat, or fiering on either part I have yielded for once to this <hi>childish sport;</hi> and submit the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the <hi>Reader</hi> (if he be but master of his own judgement!) and had recommended this the week before the <hi>last week,</hi> but that I looked for another flight of the same, or of the like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this <hi>
                  <hi>Parallel.</hi> Agesilaus</hi> King of <hi>Sparta</hi> was a prudent and brave Souldier, and yet with his children he would ride on a <hi>Hobby-horse,</hi> but a friend of his espying it, <hi>Agesilaus</hi> desired him to forbear his censure till he had some children of his own; and so I make it my request to my brethren till the case becomes their own. And shall yield him with <hi>Nicostratus</hi> to his emulous Corrival of Art <hi>Laodocus,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>Great</hi> in the LEAST ART, and I LEAST in the <hi>Greatest;</hi> the Lord make us <hi>both</hi> better! and fitter for his service!</p>
            <p>The <hi>tail</hi> of the <hi>Kite</hi> is short (<hi>p.</hi> 6.) and serves for little, unless like a <hi>Fox-tail</hi> to make a <hi>dufl!</hi> Indeed I do hope from my writings, he hath not cause to charge me <hi>with Passion and apprehensions of Sanctity in my self above others,</hi> as he would insinuate; it is true my stile is quick and terse! but truly my spirit is with fear and trembling least I should offend. As to the last; I am kept in a continual sence of my own no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thingness and vileness! at the Lord's precious feet <hi>(quia habet aures in pedibus)</hi> by prayer! and am far from such <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptuous Conceits.</hi> As to the first; I cannot excuse the <hi>rashness,</hi> naughtiness and <hi>folly</hi> of my spirit! it is my shame!
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119144:6"/>my burthen! and infirmity! which keeps me low, and with many tears! but by charging mine, let not Mr. <hi>H.</hi> think to discharge his own. <hi>Ludus enim genuit trepidum Certamen &amp; iram.</hi> And for future, if he please, let us be more seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; (as the story saith of the <hi>two Goats</hi> on a <hi>narrow bridge,</hi> the one lay down whiles the other ran over him and so es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped) I shall rather lye down with the Cause, then keep up with the Contention. But because of the <hi>greatness of his spirit</hi> (as appears in's <hi>Apol.</hi> to the <hi>Reader</hi>) I may have leave to say with <hi>Arist.</hi> to <hi>Alex.</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the indignation of such great and gallant souls is wont to fall upon Superiours, not Inferiours, or on Equals. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, seeing no man may be your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peer. — <hi>sed Nugis addere pondus.</hi> We both desire a <hi>Commonwealth!</hi> an excellent! wise! and <hi>Popular</hi> one! an <hi>Equal</hi> and a just one! but the <hi>Rule</hi> to effect it is hard to adhere to! for to add equal things to <hi>unequal,</hi> makes the <hi>whole unequal</hi> (is a <hi>Mathematic. Demonstration;</hi>) so to give us up <hi>to the spirit of the Nation</hi> (without discrimination) is unjust, <hi>unequal</hi> and destructive to the Cause and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth: but the <hi>Spirit of Christ</hi> and <hi>Adherents</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> the sound, best, ablest and holiest in the body of <hi>People</hi> and of <hi>Parliament</hi>) will preserve them <hi>
                  <hi>both.</hi> Est modus in rebus! sunt certi denique <hi>fines!</hi> Quos ultra citraque nequit consisterc <hi>Rectum.</hi>
               </hi> The true <hi>mean</hi> observed! and true <hi>ends</hi> preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved! our highest Ambition is but such <hi>foundation</hi> as does best consist with the Word of God, and with <hi>subjection</hi> to our dearest Jesus Christ! both in the <hi>constitution</hi> and <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministrations</hi> of <hi>Government</hi> to the <hi>Weal</hi> of all, both of <hi>men</hi> as men, <hi>Christians</hi> as such, and benefits of the very <hi>Beast</hi> in the field, or <hi>whole Creation</hi> which groaneth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. Not loosing the use of those <hi>distinguishing Characters</hi> God hath made, and <hi>Mercies</hi> he hath given us in! with due and <hi>equal</hi> encouragement and protection to <hi>all Believers</hi> alike; though under different perswasions in Circumstances and Discipline, holding fast to the <hi>
                  <hi>head</hi> Jesus Christ;</hi> and not that one Party, opinion or Perswasion be set up for a <hi>National Rule</hi> or Standard over another. And this, is the <hi>Holy,</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119144:6"/>Comprehensive, just and <hi>equal Commonwealth</hi> that we contend for, which we should find to be the <hi>only constant</hi> and <hi>stable</hi> too under all shakings! <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28. <hi>Isai.</hi> 33.6. and past the hazard of all Contradiction! either in <hi>Reason!</hi> or in <hi>Religion!</hi> But to period this Youthful exercise with a Youth's Answer! When a friend had promised him such a <hi>Cock</hi> of the <hi>Game</hi> as would never yield, but <hi>first dye in the place!</hi> O no! (saith he) <hi>No Sir! but such a one rather</hi> (I would have) <hi>as would <hi>never die!</hi> but kill others in the Place!</hi> And so say we, not such a <hi>Commonwealth</hi> as will die in the Place! (that did <hi>Lacedemon, Athens</hi> and others; that were destroyed by other People! or their own Divisions!) but such a <hi>one</hi> (we would have) as will <hi>never die!</hi> nor be destroyed! but will destroy all others that fight against it! <hi>Isai.</hi> 54.17. <hi>Zach.</hi> 10.4, 5. and 12.3. and 14.2, 3. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.44. This is promised by the <hi>Almighty!</hi> we hope endeavoured by the <hi>mighty</hi> in Parliament! and Army! and when performed, the <hi>Controversie</hi> is <hi>ended!</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>— &amp; verbum non amplius Addam.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>To the judicious Reader.</head>
            <p>SInce my last <hi>Concertation</hi> with Mr. <hi>P. B.</hi> and <hi>H.</hi> for a <hi>Christian Commonwealth,</hi> I am condemned (unkindly) to run the <hi>Gantlet,</hi> and endure the <hi>Strapado</hi> of mens Tongues! and squalid apprehensions! of such especially as tie knots in <hi>Bulrushes!</hi> But I chearfully submit; and must confess in many places I suited <hi>expressions</hi> to the Persons, Subject, and things before me! rather then to my own fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty or function! And to refresh the <hi>Reader</hi> with a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant Word, jest, or excrescence of Wit here and there! that upon another Subject (more noble and Divine) had not been fit, or of weight! which some will yet think too light and vain, and I only say for it, That <hi>grave</hi> cloaths (so a habit of Words!) do as little become children, as <hi>childish</hi> do <hi>grave
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119144:7"/>men.</hi> Others that haye a <hi>thirst of Revenge</hi> to quench! have made an Invasion upon my Name and Innocency, as an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to Magistracy and Ministry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which as it is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ungrounded and devised by my enemies, so I profess before the great <hi>Searcher of hearts,</hi> that I prefer those two high and bleffed Ordinances of God with us, above the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon lights and benefits <hi>of the <hi>Sun</hi> to rule by day and the <hi>Moon</hi> by night!</hi> Gen. 1. As the Necessities and Complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Times</hi> have put me (for want of a better) upon this <hi>Subject</hi> (so excentick to my spirit! and ecstatical to my work (which is most sweet, when it is most with God, and least with men! and) rather in the matters of the Gospel! then of Government!) so I shall determine (without the like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion or great Provocation for the Common service) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede in silence! until we can be warmed with the <hi>better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences</hi> of a more benigne G— and warranted or invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by a friendlier countenance from <hi>Authority.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, all I desire is (for this once) to weigh Circumstances! and award prejudices! Pick out the <hi>good</hi> and leave the <hi>bad!</hi> or at least but <hi>balance</hi> the one with the other, and I shall submit it to the <hi>Censure</hi> of my veriest Enemies. For I beg it of men to reade that <hi>wisely,</hi> which I write like a <hi>Fool!</hi> But I beg it of the Lord, that I may write that most <hi>wisely,</hi> which some reade like <hi>Fools</hi> or inconsiderate Censors. And so I remain ready and devoted, to pay all I owe to the <hi>Publick</hi> by <hi>service</hi> or by <hi>silence;</hi> to be reputed <hi>any thing:</hi> or <hi>nothing</hi> (or worse then <hi>nothing</hi>) so I may be but <hi>Christs</hi> and my <hi>Countries</hi> in every thing.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. Rogers</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>